<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel Kmak blog</title>
    <description>Find unique stories</description>
    <link>http://danielkmak.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://danielkmak.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 23:22:27 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 23:22:27 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>50 Shades of Programming: What if Christian Grey were a programmer?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-shades/girls.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;chapter-title&quot;&gt;Chapter One&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“You can leave anytime. The helicopter is on stand-by to take you whenever you want to go, you can stay the night and go home in the morning. It’s fine whatever you decide. You don’t yet know what you’re in for. You could still run for the hills. Come, I want to show you my playroom.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Just open the damn door, Christian.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He opens the door and stands back to let me in. I gaze at him once more. I so want to know what’s in here. Taking a deep breath I walk in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it feels like as if i lost myself in NASA headquarters. Everywhere are electronic devices. In the centre of the red room there is a bed. In the twilight, I can see the light from the monitors. It’s soft, slightly red. He’s definitely using Flux. Does he spend all nights in this room? &lt;i&gt;Holy fuck&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“You’ve got so much technology here. Why do you need this vast amount of electronic devices in your home?”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“I trust only computers. I like to play with them. There’s logic behind their thinking… Sometimes I wonder if there’s something wrong with me. Perhaps I’ve spent too long in the company of computer programs, and consequently my ideals and expectations are far too high.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was scared. Is he some kind of sociopath? I can agree that computers can be more predictable than humans, but why have an army of PCs in your bedroom? Something’s not right. I was standing there all the time. I’ve made only few steps from entrance towards the centre of the room. Should I turn back? It’s not safe here. Suddenly, I’ve heard a voice which brought me back from my head to reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“You look frightened. Don’t worry. I’m not some kind of dictator. I don’t want to take control over the world using an army of robots. This… this is just how I relax… I program after the work. I didn’t want to scare you.“&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to take a leap of faith and stay, but I’ve turned towards the exit. He was standing next to the door observing my every move. I came close to him. I put my hand into his pocket, grasped the phone and yanked it out as it was burning hot. I texted my friend, Kate, that I won’t be coming home tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Okay. Open the editor, Christian.” — I said when I cooled down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He opened a Vim. I knew there was no exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;chapter-title&quot;&gt;Chapter Two&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-shades/room.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been meeting for 2 months now. He wants me to sign a contract. He gave me a copy of an agreement. We’re going to negotiate the terms. He wants me to be his “submissive”. He doesn’t know yet that I’m the one who’s going to get his autograph on the contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned more about him. He’s very charming, but stays in home or in the office mosts of his time. He doesn’t want to go on dates like normal people do. He doesn’t trust third-parties, not even open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“I don’t trust open source anymore. You shouldn’t too. My heart is bleeding every time I remember OpenSSL fail.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know that someone could knew as much as him about programming before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“You’re man with a class. In the past I’ve met various men, but none of them were  like you. You’re exceptional.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Never trust a man who does not know a difference between Java and JavaScript, Anastasia. It’s very hard to grow up to decent developer when you meet only mean mercenaries, or Q&amp;amp;A programming trolls. You should search for a real man on StackOverflow.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to show him my real face. I liked him, but he wanted too much from me…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“I didn’t tell you, but I’m a recruiter. I want you to sign a contract.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“No, it goes the other way. You’re the one signing contract, that you willingly surrender yourself to me, in all things. Why didn’t you tell me earlier? I have to punish you. We will program in COBOL.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was really pissed off. I couldn’t stand that. I will never program in COBOL. It was time to give up on him. At least for a while, to give him time to reconsider his behaviour…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;chapter-title&quot;&gt;Chapter Three&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-shades/girl-window-dark.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was standing next to the window. Storm was raging outside. Christian was sitting on his chair and programming. I know he doesn’t like to be disturbed, but I had enough of this silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Why don’t you like when someone touches your code?” — I asked him.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“It’s no longer the same, Anastasia.” — he replied without even looking at me. Then he paused for a while. He stood up. His eyes were sad. Has he survived something terrible in the past? He looked at me and continued: &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“You have to get through lots of spaghetti code to find your perfect project. I’ve found one. I won’t let anyone distort its architecture. Take for example, using exceptions as regular flow of control. I’ve seen the things, Anastasia… I’m no longer the same person.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“That’s insane. How could someone program like this? What about you? Do you use exceptions at all, Christian?” &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Yes, sometimes I make an exception and answer stupid question.” — he replied rudely. Then he became quiet. He was confused. Did he hide something?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Do you really want to see my 50 fucking shades, Anastasia?”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Show me all of them, only then I can fully understand you.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“When I was a child I used to use shortcuts for variable names: a, i, evt, tmp, arr. I did it. I was programming in such way that no one could understand what I’ve written. I’ve considered myself magician. This is brutal truth about myself. I’ve used go-to programming… They said it’s good. Spaghetti was my second name and I was proud of it. When I had to do TDD — I’ve used timeouts in them… I’ve even used sleep() to work around Elastic Search index refreshing problems. And last… I’m really bad person… I… I… I’m the one who had thrown exceptions and used them to control flow.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;“Then throw me like I’m one of your exceptions.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://danielkmak.com/blog/programming/storytelling/novel/2017/05/29/50-shades-of-programming-what-if-christian-grey-were-a-programmer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://danielkmak.com/blog/programming/storytelling/novel/2017/05/29/50-shades-of-programming-what-if-christian-grey-were-a-programmer.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>storytelling</category>
        
        <category>novel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What will happen when we run out of names for JavaScript frameworks?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, I’m humble developer who works with a lot of JavaScript frameworks, libraries, modules, addons, plugins, browsers, preprocessors, processors, postprocessors, plugins for processors (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/postcss/autoprefixer&quot;&gt;Autoprefixer&lt;/a&gt;), plugins for browsers (&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/ember-inspector/bmdblncegkenkacieihfhpjfppoconhi&quot;&gt;Ember inspector&lt;/a&gt;), plugins for libraries (&lt;a href=&quot;http://jquery.com/&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt;), addons for frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it a lot of tools that we need to work with on daily basis? How big is your package.json file? Do you know what each dependency is doing? I’ve assumed here that all of them have a purpose in your project. So this is an assumption, and here’s the fact — each of them has name, which you probably need to remember. Some describe its usage — like anti-ecological &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/tree-kill&quot;&gt;tree-kill&lt;/a&gt;, some not. It could take forever to guess what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/forever&quot;&gt;forever&lt;/a&gt; is doing. Some names are similar but serve different purpose, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/pad-left&quot;&gt;pad-left&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/lpad&quot;&gt;lpad&lt;/a&gt;. Can you guess without clicking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/ducks.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;JavaScript developers pictured trying to find their way around in node_modules directory :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we see — there’s a lot of JavaScript third party code that you can use in your code. And it’s going to be more and more of that. And people will need to find new names. Programmers are not necessairly language teachers. Well, at least human language teachers. Well, umm, okay, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.italki.com/article/281/learning-english-by-learning-programming&quot;&gt;this guy is&lt;/a&gt;. So, he can name his library as he likes, because he’s entitled to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rest of us instead of finding well-suited names, often take random words and use it as name for our code. We, the programmers, like certain words more than the others. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/wrapper&quot;&gt;wrapper&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/bin-wrapper&quot;&gt;bin-wrapper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/do-wrapper&quot;&gt;do-wrapper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/word-wrapper&quot;&gt;word-wrapper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/events-wrapper&quot;&gt;events-wrapper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/circuit-breaker-wrapper&quot;&gt;circuit-breaker-wrapper&lt;/a&gt;). There’s even a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/rapper&quot;&gt;rapper&lt;/a&gt;. But it’s not normal rapper like Eminem, it’s more like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Construct wrappers around api RESTful endpoints (Browser/Angular/Node)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically rapper will give you wrapper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/rapper.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;It’s not the kind of rapper you’d expect from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/rapper&quot;&gt;rapper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know JavaScript is a popular language. There might be more than &lt;strong&gt;100 000 people&lt;/strong&gt; who use it on daily basis. Whether they use it in their job or just to make coffee (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/coffee-maker&quot;&gt;coffee-maker&lt;/a&gt;). It has a place in daily developer (and computer user) life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, JavaScript and its earlier version — Java are already becoming mature enough to use it for more than just programmatically finding good place to eat &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/burrito&quot;&gt;burrito&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/burrito.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s this game — think of any random word from English language — if there’s such JavaScript library — you drink. If you don’t want to get drunk too fast, stay at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s going to be more and more libraries and we’ll sooner or later run out of names for them. I believe it could hit us earlier than &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Year_2038_problem&quot;&gt;year 2038 problem&lt;/a&gt;. Why? We know JavaScript is state of mind. Programmers have kids. It’s a fact, you can’t argue. Kids usually acquire state of mind from their parents. Which means population of JavaScript developers can grow very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/meme.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_centered&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;JavaScript is more than a language, it’s a drug&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-maths&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Maths&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today there are 100k JavaScript developers. They’ve managed to produce &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.modulecounts.com/&quot;&gt;almost 500 000 node modules&lt;/a&gt; in 21 years (JavaScript was born in 1995, shit, older than me). We’ll take 20 for simpler maths (I’ve finished only high school, don’t require more from me). There’s like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/explore/how-many-words-are-there-in-the-english-language&quot;&gt;200 000 words in English&lt;/a&gt;. According to maths we’re already doomed (500k &amp;gt; 200k === true). But let’s assume you can build sentences from words — this gives us more options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/maths.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: take &lt;strong&gt;stupid&lt;/strong&gt; and other words and it’ll make your library name. Like: &lt;strong&gt;stupid&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;+&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;dictionary&lt;/strong&gt; = &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/stupid-dictionary&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stupid-dictionary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Yeah, dictionary can totally be stupid. What’s also stupid or frustrating. Maybe &lt;strong&gt;delay&lt;/strong&gt;. Yeah, why not, waiting and delays definitely suck. Let’s combine &lt;strong&gt;stupid + delay&lt;/strong&gt;. Here we go, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/stupid-delay&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stupid-delay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! Oh, no, both already taken! Time is running away. Pardon, names are running away!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to be quick! Back to maths! 100k developers, 500k modules, 20 years, 200k words. If, on average, every developer has 2 kids. This means that in 20 another years, in 2037 (year before 2038 year problem!!!) these kids will become new JavaScript developers. This means that we’ll have 100k developers + 200k new-born developers = 300k JavaScript developers. Also, according to maths, before 2037, current 100k developers will produce another 500k modules (like they did 1995–2017). This means we will have already 1 million modules, 300k JavaScript developers, and still only 200k English words. In another 20 years (2037–2057) 300k developers will produce 3 times more modules — 1.5 million. Wrapping ( ͡° ͜ʖ ͡°) it up we’ll have following numbers in 2057:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;300 thousand JavaScript developers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.5 million node modules&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;200 thousand English words (insufficient)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 big problem with names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you agree with me now that we need to take care of this problem before our kids have to! We can’t leave them with this ultra-hard-to-solve problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/module-counts.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;potential-solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We can start generating hashes and uuids for new JavaScript frameworks. Imagine 2 developers talking to each other:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;italic clear-list-style&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;- Hey, I’m new to programming, which framework is the best for creating single page applications?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;- Hello, I believe 77c29bcb-6422–462b-bb0f-1ba9fb1430cb is the best, but at work we use e778a475–7009–4fbd-9d83–16ebe6ef713d for its speed and flexibility. Other popular choices are b63e83ce-c6e5–4569-a8dc-b4ad34ffbb7e, c5b8999c-999f-4c8a-811a-d93f77ef5687 and d33df2b9–9325–434a-a507–988cce172cde. Hope I’ve helped!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;- That’s great! Thanks a lot!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/digits.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. We can use QR codes, images, author’s voice sample, something unique and put it instead of name in our package.json.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/rapper.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Libraries could be identified by their authors rapping&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. We can try to unify everything as Romans tried or Esperanto. Merging every module out there to Node API or browser API seems like a good idea for a start. We could get rid of all dependencies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/romans.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. Humanity will repent, abandon all modules, go back to Vanilla JS and salvation to JavaScript will be granted through minimalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/post-js-fws/pilgrim.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 16:31:08 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://danielkmak.com/blog/programming/javascript/2017/05/06/what-will-happen-when-we-run-out-of-names-for-javascript-frameworks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://danielkmak.com/blog/programming/javascript/2017/05/06/what-will-happen-when-we-run-out-of-names-for-javascript-frameworks.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
